<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
    "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY legal SYSTEM "legal.xml">
  <!ENTITY appversion "2.12">
  <!ENTITY manrevision "2.8">
  <!ENTITY date "June 2004">
  <!ENTITY app "<application>Quadrapassel</application>">
  <!ENTITY appname "Quadrapassel">
  <!ENTITY version "2.8"> 
]>

<!-- 
      (Do not remove this comment block.)
  Maintained by the GNOME Documentation Project
  http://developer.gnome.org/projects/gdp
  Template version: 2.0 beta
  Template last modified Feb 12, 2002
-->

<!-- =============Document Header ============================= -->

<article id="index" lang="en">
<!-- please do not change the id; for translations, change lang to -->
<!-- appropriate code -->
  <articleinfo>
    <title>&app; Manual</title>

    <abstract role="description">
      <para>
	Quadrapassel is GNOME's version of Tetris, the classic game of 
	interlocking four-piece blocks. As they fall from the top, 
	the player must orient them to fit the other blocks at the 
	bottom so that they form a complete horizontal line, in which 
	case that line disappears and the player gains points.
      </para>
    </abstract>

    <copyright>
      <year>2004</year>
      <holder>Angela Boyle</holder>
    </copyright>

  <!-- translators: uncomment this:

  <copyright>
   <year>2000</year>
   <holder>ME-THE-TRANSLATOR (Latin translation)</holder>
  </copyright>

   -->
<!-- An address can be added to the publisher information.  If a role is 
     not specified, the publisher/author is the same for all versions of the 
     document.  -->
    <publisher> 
      <publishername> GNOME Documentation Project </publishername> 
    </publisher> 

   &legal;
   <!-- This file  contains link to license for the documentation (GNU FDL),
and 
        other legal stuff such as "NO WARRANTY" statement. Please do not change 
	any of this. -->
	
    <authorgroup> 
      <author role="maintainer"> 
	<firstname>Angela</firstname> 
	<surname>Boyle</surname> 
	<affiliation> 
	  <address> <email>anjela@u.washington.edu</email> </address> 
	</affiliation> 
      </author> 
<!-- This is appropriate place for other contributors: translators,
      maintainers,  etc. Commented out by default.
       <othercredit role="translator">
	<firstname>Latin</firstname> 
	<surname>Translator 1</surname> 
	<affiliation> 
	  <orgname>Latin Translation Team</orgname> 
	  <address> <email>translator@gnome.org</email> </address> 
	</affiliation>
	<contrib>Latin translation</contrib>
      </othercredit>
-->
    </authorgroup>
	
	<releaseinfo revision="2.26" role="review"/>

    <revhistory>
      <revision> 
	<revnumber>&appname; Manual V&manrevision;</revnumber> 
	<date>&date;</date> 
	<revdescription> 
	  <para role="author">Angela Boyle
	    <email>anjela@u.washington.edu</email>
	  </para>
	  <para role="publisher">GNOME Documentation Project</para>
	</revdescription> 
      </revision> 
    </revhistory> 

    <releaseinfo>This manual describes version &appversion; of &appname;.
    </releaseinfo>
    <!-- The following feedback information only applies to applications
    listed in bugzilla.gnome.org and bugzilla.ximian.com. For other
    applications, please provide your own feedback info or remove this
    section altogether -->
    <legalnotice> 
      <title>Feedback</title> 
      <para>To report a bug or make a suggestion regarding the &app;
application or
	this manual, follow the directions in the 
	<ulink url="ghelp:user-guide?feedback-bugs"
	  type="help">GNOME Feedback Page</ulink>. 
      </para>
<!-- Translators may also add here feedback address for translations -->
    </legalnotice>

  </articleinfo>

  <indexterm zone="index"> 
    <primary>Quadrapassel</primary> 
  </indexterm>

<!-- ==============================Document Body==================-->

<sect1 id="s1-intro">
 <title>Introduction</title>

<!--synopsis of game-->
  <para><application>Quadrapassel</application> comes from the classic falling-block game, <application>Tetris</application>. The goal of the game is to create complete horizontal lines of blocks, which will disappear. The blocks come in seven different shapes made from four blocks each: one straight, two L-shaped, one square, and two S-shaped. The blocks fall from the top center of the screen in a random order. You rotate the blocks and move them across the screen to drop them in complete lines. You score by dropping blocks fast and completing lines. As your score gets higher, you level up and the blocks fall faster.</para>

<!--running game-->
   <para>To run <application>Quadrapassel</application>, select <menuchoice><guimenu>Applications</guimenu><guisubmenu>Games</guisubmenu><guimenuitem>Quadrapassel</guimenuitem></menuchoice>, or type <command>quadrapassel</command> in the command line.</para>

<!--part of gnome-games-->
   <para><application>Quadrapassel</application> is included in the <filename>gnome-games</filename> package, which is part of the GNOME desktop environment. This document describes version &version; of <application>Quadrapassel</application>.</para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="s1-playing">
 <title>Playing <application>Quadrapassel</application></title>
  <para>You can score through two actions: completing lines and dropping blocks quickly. </para>
   <sect2 id="s2-block-moving">
     <title> Moving the Blocks</title>
      <para>To play the game, you only need the four arrow keys.</para>
       <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
         <para><keycap>Left</keycap> and <keycap>Right</keycap> move the block correspondingly across the screen.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
         <para><keycap>Up</keycap> rotates the block. The default rotation is counterclockwise. You can change the rotation under <menuchoice><guimenu>Settings</guimenu><guimenuitem>Preferences</guimenuitem></menuchoice> and deselecting <guilabel>Rotate blocks counterclockwise</guilabel>.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
         <para><keycap>Down</keycap> and the <keycap>Space Bar</keycap> move the block down the screen faster.<keycap>Down</keycap> moves the block down faster. <keycap>Space-bar</keycap> moves the block directly to the bottom.</para>
        </listitem>
       </itemizedlist> 
   </sect2>
   <sect2 id="s2-newgame">
     <title>Starting a New Game</title>
      <para>To begin a new game, go to <menuchoice><guimenu>Game</guimenu><guimenuitem>New Game</guimenuitem></menuchoice>. The game will begin dropping blocks from the center of the top of the window. The default start-up of the game has no blocks in the game window and shows the next block that will fall in the upper right hand corner. <guilabel>Score</guilabel> shows the number of points you have earned. <guilabel>Lines</guilabel> shows the number of lines you have completed. <guilabel>Level</guilabel> shows the level of difficulty you are on.</para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="s2-pausegame">
     <title>Pausing the Game</title>
      <para>To pause your game, go to <menuchoice><guimenu>Game</guimenu><guimenuitem>Pause Game</guimenuitem></menuchoice>. You can only pause a game when you are playing. The time limit on pausing your game is unlimited. To unpause the game, go back to <menuchoice><guimenu>Game</guimenu><guimenuitem>Pause Game</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.</para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="s2-endgame">
     <title>Ending the Game</title>
      <para>Go to <menuchoice><guimenu>Game</guimenu><guimenuitem>End Game</guimenuitem></menuchoice> to end your current game without quiting Quadrapassel.</para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="s2-quitgame">
     <title>Quiting the <application>Quadrapassel</application></title>
      <para>To completely quit <application>Quadrapassel</application> go to <menuchoice><guimenu>Game</guimenu><guimenuitem>Quit</guimenuitem></menuchoice>. If you are in the middle of a game when you quit, you will end your game without saving your score.</para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="s2-scoring">
     <title>Scoring Points</title>
     <para>You score points through two methods: dropping blocks faster and deleting complete lines of blocks. When you delete lines, you get more points, but dropping blocks faster will quickly add up. As you level up, the blocks will begin falling faster. The highest level is 10, at which point you will only have just over a second to manipulate each block.</para>
    </sect2> 
    <sect2 id="s2-pastscores">
     <title>Viewing Past Scores</title>
      <para>You can view the top ten scores played on your computer through <menuchoice><guimenu>Game</guimenu><guimenuitem>Scores</guimenuitem></menuchoice>. The names of the users are shown next the their score and the date they played.</para>
    </sect2> 
</sect1>

 
<sect1 id="s1-customizegame">
 <title>Customizing <application>Quadrapassel</application></title>
  <sect2 id="s2-customstartup">
   <title>Customizing Game Start-up</title>
    <para>By going to <menuchoice><guimenu>Settings</guimenu><guimenuitem>Preferences</guimenuitem></menuchoice>, you can customize a variety of features for the start-up of each Quadrapassel game: number and density of pre-filled rows, and starting level. "Pre-filled rows" refers to how many rows will already have blocks in them when you start each new game.</para>
    <sect3 id="s3-numberpfr">
     <title>Number of Pre-filled Rows</title>
      <para>You can change the number of rows that already have blocks at the start-up of each new game by using the spin box. You can start with up to 19 rows pre-filled at the start-up of your game. The default number of pre-filled rows is zero.</para>
     </sect3>
     <sect3 id="s3-densitypfr">
      <title>Density of Pre-filled Rows</title>
       <para>You can change the density of the blocks in the pre-filled rows at the start-up of each game. You can choose a density up to 10 blocks. You should first choose how many rows you want pre-filled under <guilabel>Number of Pre-filled Rows</guilabel>. The default density of blocks is three.</para>
     </sect3>
     <sect3 id="s3-startlevel">
      <title>Level to Start On</title>
       <para>You can adjust the level of difficulty you start on. The highest level you can start on is 10, which is the highest level you can play to. The default starting level is one.</para>
     </sect3>
   </sect2>
   <sect2 id="s3-customblocks">
    <title>Customizing the Gameplay</title>
    <para>From <menuchoice><guimenu>Settings</guimenu><guimenuitem>Preferences</guimenuitem></menuchoice>, you can customize a variety of features related to the blocks: previewing the next block, block colors, and block rotation.</para>
      <sect3 id="s3-sound">
	<title>Enable sounds</title>
	<para>Turn the sound effects on and off using this option. If you are playing this game in any area which you share with other people, you should probably select off.</para>
      </sect3>
     <sect3 id="s3-nextblock">
      <title>Preview Next Block</title>
        <para>Choose this option if you want to see the next block that is going to fall. This feature helps you plan the placement of your blocks.</para>
     </sect3>
     <sect3 id="s3-blockcolors">
      <title>Use Random Block Colors</title>
       <para>Choose if you want the various block configurations to be color coded or randomly colored. If you use the colors to help you identify blocks, random colors will make the game more difficult.</para>
     </sect3>
     <sect3 id="s3-difficult-block-mode">
      <title>Choose Difficult Blocks</title>
       <para>Choose this option if you want to select mode that is designed specifically to annoy the player. With this feature enabled, you never get the piece you want, and very seldom complete a row. Next block preview doesn't correspond to actual piece you get next, but to the one you probably wish to get.</para>
     </sect3>
     <sect3 id="s3-block-rotation">
      <title>Rotate Blocks Counterclockwise</title>
       <para>Choose this option if you want the blocks to rotate counterclockwise or not.</para>
     </sect3>
     <sect3 id="s3-show-target">
      <title>Show where the block will land</title>
        <para>If this feature is used a grey image of the block will
  show you where the block will land. This feature is very useful for
  beginning players, but experienced players will find it a
  distraction.
       </para>
     </sect3>
   </sect2>
   <sect2 id="s2-customlook">
    <title>Customizing the Look of <application>Quadrapassel</application></title>
    <para>Under <menuchoice><guimenu>Settings</guimenu><guimenuitem>Preferences</guimenuitem></menuchoice>, you can customize the look of <application>Quadrapassel</application>: images for the blocks.</para>
     <sect3 id="s3-blockimage">
      <title>Block Image</title>
       <para>You can change the style of the blocks, including image and size. There are a variety of pre-made styles.</para>
     </sect3>
     <sect3 id="s3-background">
       <title>Background</title> <para>If you drag your favorite image
       into the <application>Quadrapassel</application> window it will be
       used as the background. If you want a solid color as the
       background drag one in from either the color picker or from
       <application>nautlilus'</application> <guimenuitem>Backgrounds
       and Emblems</guimenuitem> dialog (the reset item from that
       dialog also works).</para>
     </sect3>
    </sect2>
   </sect1>

<sect1 id="authors">
  <title>Authors</title>
  <para>
   <application>Quadrapassel</application> was written by J. Marcin Gorycki
   in 1999 and maintained by Gnome Games Team since then. This manual was
   written by Angela Boyle.
   To report a bug or make a suggestion regarding this application or
   this manual, follow the directions in this
   <ulink url="ghelp:user-guide?feedback-bugs" type="help">document</ulink>.
  </para>

  <!-- For translations: uncomment this:

  <para>
   Latin translation was done by ME
   (<email>MYNAME@MYADDRESS</email>). Please send all  comments  and
   suggestions regarding this translation to SOMEWHERE.
  </para>

  -->
</sect1>


 <!-- ============= Application License ============================= -->

 <sect1 id="s1-license">
  <title>License</title>
  <para>This program is free software; you can redistribute it and/or modify it under the terms of the  <ulink type="help" url="gnome-help:gpl"> <citetitle>GNU General Public License</citetitle></ulink> as published by the Free Software Foundation;  either version 2 of the License, or (at your option) any later version.
  </para>
  <para>This program is distributed in the hope that it will be useful, but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the <citetitle>GNU General Public License</citetitle> for more details.
  </para>
  <para>A copy of the <citetitle>GNU General Public License</citetitle> is included as an appendix to the <citetitle>GNOME Users Guide</citetitle>.  You may also obtain a copy of the <citetitle>GNU General Public License</citetitle> from the Free Software Foundation by visiting <ulink type="http" url="http://www.fsf.org">their Web site</ulink> or by writing to
   <address>
    Free Software Foundation, Inc.
    <street>59 Temple Place</street> - Suite 330
    <city>Boston</city>, <state>MA</state> <postcode>02111-1307</postcode>
    <country>USA</country>
   </address>
  </para>
 </sect1>
</article>
